<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Eighth collection of papers relating to the present juncture of affairs in England</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E265B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19509</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12289357</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12289357</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58858</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38251)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58858)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1503:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Eighth collection of papers relating to the present juncture of affairs in England</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Despite the title, this collection is not one of the series of 12 published by Richard Janeway and reissued in 1689 with general title: A compleat collection of papers in twelve parts ... An advertisement on verso of t.p. of Janeway's 6th collection warns of spurious 6th and 7th collections published by R. Baldwin; the present collection is another item in Baldwin's series. 'An account of several papers that have been collected' (caption title, p. 33-34) lists the contents of Janeway's first 5 collections and Baldwin's collections 6-8, implying that all were issued as parts of the same series"--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained with loss of print. Pages 14-31 from defective Union Theological Seminary Library, New York, copy spliced at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>(from t.p.) I. The tryal and examination of the test of the Church of England's loyalty -- II. Some reflections upon the additional libel, intituled, An instance of the Church of England's loyalty -- III. The pedigree of popery, or, Genealogy of Antichrist -- IV. A letter to a person of quality, occasion'd by the news of the ensuing Parliament -- V. Father La Chaise's project for the extirpation of hereticks: in a letter from him to Father Petres -- VI. An account of the papers that have been collected, relating to the present juncture of affairs.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58858:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58858:1"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>AN Eighth Collection OF PAPERS Relating to the Preſent Juncture of Affairs in</hi> England: <hi>VIZ.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>I.</hi> The Tryal and Examination of the Teſt of the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Loyalty.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>II.</hi> Some Reflections upon the Additional Libel, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>An Inſtance of the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>'s Loyalty.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>III.</hi> The Pedigree of Popery, or Genealogy of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>IV.</hi> A Letter to a Perſon of Quality, occaſion'd by the News of the Enſuing Parliament.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>V.</hi> Father <hi>La Chaiſe</hi>'s Project for the Extirpation of Hereticks: In a Letter from him to Father <hi>Petres.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>VI.</hi> An Account of the Papers that have been Collected, relating to the preſent Juncture of Affairs.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Licenſed according to Order.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed</hi> Anno Domini, 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58858:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58858:2"/>
            <head>The Tryal and Examination of a late Libel, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>A New Teſt of the Church of</hi> England's <hi>Loyalty.</hi> With ſome Reflections upon the Additional Libel, intituled, <hi>An Inſtance of the Church of</hi> England's <hi>Loyalty.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Church of <hi>England</hi> has of late years eſpecially been on the charitable ſide towards the Papiſts, and has allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to be Chriſtians and not Anti-Chriſtians, nay to be a true Church and not the Synagogue of Satan; and ſeemed to have utterly forgotten the two fundamental points of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, <hi>That Hereticks are to be purſued with Fire and Sword,</hi> which was determined by the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council, under <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, and conſcientiouſly practiſed ever ſince; And <hi>that Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks,</hi> which the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> determined in the caſe of <hi>John Huſs,</hi> and <hi>Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague:</hi> And in this exceſs of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which hopeth all things and believeth all things, they have hoped againſt hope, and have exerciſed ſtrong acts of Faith where no Faith is, neither have they had any apprehenſions of being deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but rather of being ſaved and protected with Fire and Sword. But finding in great meaſure their Charity miſtaken, to the end that all their diſappointments may ſeem juſt upon them, they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently taxed with <hi>Diſloyalty.</hi> So <hi>Aeſops</hi> Lamb, when ſhe was to be eaten, was charged by the Wolf for muddying the upper part of the ſtream which was far above her. In Vindication therefore of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and to ſhew her innocency in this point, I ſhall examine this new Teſt of the Church of <hi>England's</hi> Loyalty, where ſhe is tried and caſt, weighed in the Balance and found light, but, to our comfort, it is by deceitfull weights and meaſures.</p>
            <p>The firſt device is to pretend, <q rend="inline">That the Church of <hi>England</hi> appropriate to themſelves alone the principles of true Loyalty, and that no other Church or Communion on earth can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Monarchy, or indeed with any Government. This is a preſumption of ſo high a nature, that it renders the Church of <hi>England</hi> a deſpicable Enemy to the reſt of mankind. </q>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That the Church of <hi>England</hi> is here repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by that which is the true Character of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which has all along been a known Engroſſer. Which pretends to have all Faith, and all Holineſs, and will have all Heaven to her
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58858:3"/> ſelf, and pretending to have the Keys of it, will ſuffer none other to come thither. Whereas the Church of <hi>England</hi> allows, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that all Proteſtants have true Faith and true Loyalty as well as ſhe, and the ſame Faith and Loyalty, as appears by the Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Confeſſions, but alſo that Pagans are capable of moral vertue, ſuch as Loyalty is, and have heretofore been great exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of it. Many of them have lookt upon themſelves as not born for <hi>themſelves,</hi> but for their <hi>Country,</hi> and were ſtrict obſervers of the Laws: And it is well known, that <hi>Socrates</hi> in particular had that Reverence for the Laws, that though he was put upon it by his Friends, yet he would not break them to ſave his Life. <hi>His Bones and Sinews,</hi> as his words are in <hi>Plato</hi>'s Phaedo, could eaſily have carried him into a Foreign Country, but he would not ſuffer them to do it. And therefore this Author, in ſaying that the Church of <hi>England</hi> averrs, <q rend="inline">That no other Sect or Community on Earth from the Riſing to the Setting Sun can be capable of this ſingular gift of Loyalty;</q> betrays his malice and ignorance together, and plainly ſhews, that though he make new Teſts of Loyalty, yet he does not know what Loyalty is.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>Loyal</hi> is a Term of Law, and is indifferently applied to things as well as Perſons. So a Loyal Judgment is a Judgment according to Law, and is oppoſed to a falſe Judgment. A Loyal contract is a lawfull bargain. A Man buys an Horſe in a Market, and then he has a Loyal Title, a Legal Title to him. So again, a Perſon behaves himſelf according to Law, and obſerves the Laws of the Land, and then he is a Loyal Man, he is <hi>Legalis Homo,</hi> as a Juryman is required to be, that is, ſuch a one as cannot be chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged for a Criminal, or a breaker of the Laws. And in caſe a Man's Behaviour be according to Law, it is <hi>Loyal,</hi> whether it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect a Superiour or an Inferiour. <hi>Action neſt autre choſe que Loial demand de ſon droit.</hi> An action is nothing elſe but the Loyal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of a Man's Right. <hi>Mirror,</hi> p. 115, and p. 122. A Serjeant at Law ſhall not uſe any deceits in his practice, nor conſent to them, <hi>mes Loyalment maintiendra le droit de ſon Client,</hi> &amp;c. But ſhall <hi>Loyally</hi> maintain the Right of his Client, ſo that it be not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by any folly, negligence, or default of his.</p>
            <p>From hence it follows, that Loyalty can have no other rule or meaſure but the Law; for though ſome Men love to have confuſed notions of things, and ſpeak of Loyalty as if it were a thing in the Clouds, and ſome abſtruſe matter over our Heads, yet it appears to be plain thing, and of eaſie comprehenſion, for it is nothing elſe but <hi>Conformity to the Laws.</hi> The plain Engliſh of <hi>Loyalty</hi> is <hi>lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58858:3"/> and it is utterly impoſſible that there ſhould be any other Teſt or Touchſtone, any other meaſure or ſtandard of <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> but the Law it ſelf. For if there had been no Law, as there had been no Tranſgreſſion nor Violation of it, ſo there had been no Loyalty nor Conformity to it. And therefore Loyalty againſt Law is a contradiction, it is obedience made up of diſobedience. The Law is that which makes the King our Liege Lord, and us his Liege Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and accordingly both Prince and People are mutually ſworn to the keeping of it; and our Allegiance binds us to an obedience according to Law, and not otherwiſe. To obey the King himſelf contrary to Law is Diſloyalty, and to diſobey the King in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Laws is Loyalty. If it be not thus, then all the Judges of <hi>England</hi> for theſe 340 Years and upwards, have been all <hi>Sworn to be Diſloyal.</hi> For they are ſworn <hi>to proceed according to Law, though the King by his Letters or Writs under the great Seal, or under the little Seal, or by his own mouth ſhould command them the contrary,</hi> 2. 18. 20. Ed. 3. Forteſc. c. 51. Etiamſi Rex per Literas ſuas aut Ore tenus Contrarium juſſerit. And ſo in the Court Leet, when we ſwear that <hi>we will be true Liegemen, and true Faith and Troth bear to our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lord the King, and that we ſhall no Felony nor Treaſon commit, nor thereunto aſſent, and ſhall be obedient to all the K. Majeſties Laws, Precepts and Proceſs proceeding from the ſame:</hi> It is plain, that we do not promiſe any obedience to Precepts or Proceſs which are <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to Law, or <hi>beſides</hi> the Law, and not <hi>grounded</hi> upon it; No, that is no part of our Allegiance, which you plainly ſee is <hi>limited</hi> to the Laws.</p>
            <p>Now this being the undoubted notion of Loyalty, how ſhould the Church of <hi>England</hi> ever dream of appropriating it to her ſelf, ſince obedience to the Laws of their Country has always been prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in all Nations, by all vertuous men whatſoever; it being a point of common honeſty and juſtice, that men ſhould abide by thoſe Laws, which either themſelves or their Proxies have made, and to which in one way or another they have given their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, which always concludes, and is binding to an honeſt Man: Only there is one ſort of men in the World, who can never be Loyal; becauſe <hi>no Man can ſerve two Maſters,</hi> the Government of his own Country and the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi> They who have a Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator abroad to give them new Laws, and a Diſpencer to repeal the old ones, can never be true and firm to the Laws of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Country. Their Loyalty is in Abeyance to the Pope's Laws, (which agreed even with the old Laws of <hi>England,</hi> bofore the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, <hi>like Fire and Water,</hi> as Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> proves in his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58858:4"/> large Letter to Q. <hi>Mary</hi>) and their Allegiance is pinned upon the the Pope's Sleeve. In the mean time the Church of <hi>England</hi> has very great reaſon to inſiſt upon her Loyalty, becauſe if a man be not a lawfull man, he is defeated of the benefit of the Law in many caſes: Whereas the members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are able to uſe the old legal exceptions againſt their preſent Accuſers. <hi>Siri, jeo ſuy Loial home, &amp; a la foy le Roy, &amp; ceſt provor eſt felon, &amp; hors la foy le Roy.</hi> Sirs, I am a lawfull man and in Allegiance to the King, and this Accuſer of mine is a Felon or a Traytor, and never took the Oath of Allegiance. And we are ready to joyn iſſue with them upon this point, Whether they or we be the lawfull men, and which of us are guilty of High Treaſon againſt the King and the Realm, Felony, Miſpriſion of Treaſon, Praemunire, and are utterly diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by the Law to hold any Office either Civil or Military, not only by the Statutes made in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, but alſo in the Reigns of King <hi>James,</hi> and of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second. And therefore as often as we are taxed in our Loyalty, we ſhall only ask them, what Laws we have broken? Or whether it be We or They who hate the Laws of the Land, and are continually exclaiming againſt them, and would blow them up with as good a Will, as once they attempted to blow up all the States of the Kingdom in the Parliament houſe where thoſe Laws were made, and for that very reaſon, becauſe thoſe Laws were made there. See 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> c. 1. the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute which is yearly read in our Churches on the 5th. of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus explained the true ſenſe and meaning of Loyalty, it is eaſie for every body to apply it, and to juſtifie <hi>the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land's <hi>carriage and behaviour, both in her Infancy and now in her Old Age</hi> (by the way, old Folks and threatned Folks live long) And to ſhew, that it has been according to the Laws of the Land; which if they had broken and oppoſed, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have done, they might then be charged with Diſloyalty indeed. But while they continue to keep the Laws, by the Grace of God the Laws will keep them: for ſo long the Law enables them to hold their own, they can challenge the benefit of the Law, they can claim a legal Protection, which is far better than any which is illegal and arbitrary, uncertain and precarious, and they are on the better ſide of the Hedge of all the Violators of the Law whatſoever. I ſhall not need to trouble my ſelf with the Remainder of this new Teſt, any otherwiſe than by making ſome very ſhort Notes upon the moſt remarkable paſſages in it.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58858:4"/>
            <p n="1"> I The firſt charge is, <hi>That the Church of</hi> England <hi>aſſiſted Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to invade the Crown,</hi> meaning the Lady <hi>Jane</hi> and Q. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the the firſt of theſe, I cannot ſee how it can be charged upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe the Proteſtants were divided about Q. <hi>Janes</hi> Title, ſome were for it, and ſome were againſt it, as particularly Judge <hi>Hales</hi> and the <hi>Suffolk</hi> Goſpellers, who ſtuck to Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> and were but ſorrily rewarded for it. But to wave Q. <hi>Janes</hi> caſe, and what might be ſaid concerning it from the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, 11 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. c. 1. I think this is a very fair offer, that when the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have anſwered for all the bad Titles which were ſet up in the times of <hi>Popery,</hi> which were at leaſt in the proportion of two bad ones for one good, we will then anſwer, as well as we can, for that ſingle one, which has happened ſince the time of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The other Uſurper, which the Church of</hi> England <hi>Aſſiſted to Invade the Crown, was Q.</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>a known Baſtard.</hi> It is well known that a Popiſh Parliament then ſitting, acknowledged her Title, and aſſiſted in ſetting her upon the Throne, and not the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which was then driven into Corners, and into Foreign Countries, and was not in a condition to aſſiſt any body. And whereas Q <hi>Elizabeth</hi> is ſaid to have been a <hi>known Baſtard,</hi> the Church and Court of <hi>Rome</hi> knew the contrary. For they knew that her Mothers Marriage was good, becauſe the former Marriage was naught. And the former was confeſſedly naught, becauſe it wanted the Pope's Diſpenſation and Licence, which was bought with a mighty ſumm of Money, to make it good. If it had been lawfull in it ſelf, it had not needed the Pope's Diſpenſation to make it lawfull: And we are willing to refer it to all the World, whether the Pope's Diſpenſation can make an unlawfull Marriage to be lawfull.</p>
            <p n="2">II. We are told, <hi>That the Prelatick Proteſtancy, called the Church of</hi> England, <hi>enacted thoſe bloody Canibal Laws, to Hang, Draw, and Quarter, the Prieſts of the living God.</hi> I ſuppoſe he means the Maſs Prieſts. Now theſe Canibal Laws were made to hang them, not as Prieſts, but as Traitors and Traiter-makers. But I would fain ask, Might not any Sheep-ſtealer, or Cut-purſe, in <hi>Newgate,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt Perſecution, and the bloody Canibal Laws, with a much better grace? That a Man made in the Image of God ſhould be hanged like a Dog, for ſuch trifles as a Sheep, or a little looſe Pocket-money! Whereas the Law of God only required <hi>Forefold Reſtitution</hi> in thoſe caſes; and in ſome Countries, Stealing was not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58858:5"/> only lawfull but was encouraged as an Accompliſhment. But on the other hand, in God's own Government Idolatrous Prieſts were to be put to death. And by the Law of Nations in all Countries whatſoever, Spies, Deſerters, Adherents and Emiſſaries of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Enemy (as by our Law the Pope is to us, and by his Law all Hereticks are declared to be to him) are all to be hanged up.</p>
            <p>And then as for the Maſs Prieſts being called <hi>the Prieſts of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God,</hi> I appeal to the ſenſes and underſtanding of all mankind, whether the Lord God, the Maker, the former, and the Creator of a Maſs Prieſt, whom he carries in his Box and Worſhips, be a living God or no? Nay, according to <hi>the School of the Euchariſt,</hi> I will be judged by the very Rats and Mice which often run away with him.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The next thing the Church, or rather the State of <hi>England</hi> is charged with, for it was a Parliament buſineſs at leaſt thirteen Years, is the Execution of <hi>Mary</hi> Q. of <hi>Scots,</hi> for Treaſon againſt Q. <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> Wherein if they did any thing contrary to Law, and the Allegiance due to their then preſent Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> they are chargeable with diſloyalty, otherwiſe not. And whereas this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor calls it <hi>a Barbarous Murther,</hi> and an <hi>Execrable Fact,</hi> I would deſire him to ſpeak low, for if the Laws ſhould over-hear him, they would call this, Arraigning the Juſtice of the Nation. And in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that this Fact was <hi>the firſt of the kind,</hi> he betrays great Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: he might as well have ſaid, that the Emperour <hi>Licinius,</hi> Colleague with <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, and Q. <hi>Joan</hi> of <hi>Naples,</hi> are <hi>ſtill living.</hi> And as yet I have never read, that what <hi>Conſtantine</hi> did in that caſe, was to <hi>the ſcandal and reproach of Chriſtianity,</hi> or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of thoſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> who lived under <hi>Licinius,</hi> and joyned with <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great in that Affair.</p>
            <p>But fourthly I find (which is the Subſtance of the ſixth and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Pages) that the Church of <hi>England</hi> might have all her old ſcores cleared, and all her former faults forgotten, and might paſs for Loyal ſtill, if ſhe would now conſent <hi>to the Repeal of the Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Penal Laws, which were purpoſely enacted to maintain the Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Queen</hi> Elizabeth) <hi>and the late impious Teſts.</hi> Which puts me in mind of the conditions of peace, which the Wolves ſent to the Sheep. The main Article was, that the Sheep ſhould deliver up their Dogs, which they kept for a Guard, and which were the great hindrance to a firm and laſting Peace. But every body knows how long the Peace laſted. But to proceed, <hi>If the Sanguinary Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58858:5"/> Laws were purpoſely enacted to maintain the Uſurpation of Queen</hi> Elizabeth, how came they to be enacted afreſh in the firſt year of King <hi>James,</hi> when that <hi>Uſurpation</hi> was over? How came they two years after 3 <hi>Jac. c.</hi> 1. to be called Religious and neceſſary Laws? And how came more of theſe Religious and neceſſary Laws to be made in the ſame Parliament, and in ſucceeding Parliaments? As for <hi>the late impious Teſts</hi> (choice Epithets for the Laws of the Land) they were made as appears by the Title of the Acts, <hi>To prevent dangers which may happen from Popiſh Recuſants.</hi> Now the ſheep might ſafely have parted with their Dogs, if the Peaceable Wolves at the ſame time would have parted with their <hi>Fangs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. In the laſt page he ſays, <hi>As for the Teſts themſelves, it is not my Province to ſhew the Abſurdities of them in point of Doctrine.</hi> It is well it is not, for he muſt get abundance of help whenever he goes about that Work. However he offers at it in theſe words. <q rend="inline"> Though by the by I muſt hold it a great folly, to ſay that Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not a probable opinion at the leaſt, conſidering the number and Learning of thoſe who maintain it, which is the beſt part of Chriſtendom: And if it be a probable opinion, it muſt be a great Temerity in any man to ſwear there is no ſuch thing. I had always thought that a probable opinion muſt be made out by proofs and probable reaſons, and not by numbers and telling of Noſes.</q> But it ſeems the cauſe of Tranſubſtantiation runs very low, when it muſt be maintained by ſuch Arguments, as hold much ſtronger for <hi>Paganiſm</hi> and for <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> whom all the World worſhipped. The Religion of the <hi>Heathens</hi> was of a larger extent and of longer ſtanding than Popery, and was main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by all the learning of <hi>Athens</hi> and of Ancient <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet we <hi>dare be Sworn,</hi> that it was a falſe Religion. I think we do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Tranſubſtantiation upon Oath, but only by publick De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration and Subſcription; but if we did, it would by no means be a raſh Oath. For may not I ſafely ſwear, that there is no ſuch Figure as a Square Circle, when the thing involves manifold contradictions, and it is plainly demonſtrable that the properties of a Square and of a Circle are utterly Inconſiſtent. Now we have a thouſandfold more Evidence, and are able to make as clear proof and demonſtration of it a thouſand times over, that there never was, nor is, nor can be any ſuch thing as Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is nothing elſe but a heap of Contradictions, Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, and impoſſible Falſhoods. And therefore we have the ſame aſſurance that the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation never came
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58858:6"/> nor could come from God, as we have of this clear and evident Truth, <hi>That it is impoſſible for God to Lye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VI. And now we are come to the concluſion and upſhot of the buſineſs, which is in theſe words. <q rend="inline"> So that upon the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Loyal Church of <hi>England</hi> muſt either change her old Principles of Loyalty, and take example by her Catholick Neighbours how to behave her ſelf towards a Prince who is not of her perſwaſion; or ſhe muſt give his Majeſty leave not to nouriſh a Snake in his own Boſome, but rather to withdraw his Royal Protection, which was promiſed upon the account of her conſtant Fidelity.</q> I wiſh this Author had been more expreſs and particular in this Dilemma and difficulty, to which he thinks he has reduced the Church of <hi>England;</hi> either to turn over a new leaf, and learn a new leſſon of Loyalty from her Catholick Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, or elſe to do worſe. For he does not tell us, which of our Catholick Neighbours we muſt take example by, whether Mrs. <hi>Celier,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sclater,</hi> who have both publiſhed to the World, that they turned Papiſts, that is, have made themſelves High-Traytors, for the improvement of their Loyalty; or whether we ſhould take example by this Author himſelf, to call Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth Baſtard,</hi> to ridicule <hi>an Infallible</hi> Engliſh <hi>Parliament,</hi> as he calls it in Scorn, to deprave and vilifie ſeveral Statutes, which are and will be the ſtanding Laws of the Land, till ſuch time as they are repealed by Act of Parliament: And therefore he has not been ſo clear as he might have been in this point. Which the Church of <hi>England</hi> will hardly trouble her ſelf about, becauſe ſhe likes her old Principles of Loyalty very well, and is not given to change, but knows when ſhe is well. In the mean time this Author tells us very plainly, and expreſly enough, that till the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> change their old Principles of Loyalty and take example by their Catholick Neighbours, they are to be lookt upon as a Snake in his Majeſties Boſome, and cannot expect to be protected. Alas! this Gentleman is utterly miſtaken. For a Legal Eſtabliſhment has a Right to a Legal Protection, and the King is bound both by his Oath, and by the duty of his Kingly Office to protect the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it is by Law eſtabliſhed. And therefore to talk of withdrawing Protection from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is to talk of removing the <hi>Thames</hi> to <hi>York.</hi> But we are ſo much uſed to ſuch empty threatnings and flaſhes in the Pan, that we know they will not kill. So the Reply to the <hi>Oxford</hi> Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Addreſſing threatens the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that by the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58858:6"/> Prerogative in Matters Eccleſiaſtical it may be in great meaſure <hi>Legally Subverted,</hi> p. 4. A Legal Eſtabliſhment even while it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſuch, Legally Subverted! They would make us believe, that the Laws of <hi>England</hi> were made up of Jeſuitical Equivocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and did blow Hot and Cold with the ſame mouth. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, That Replyer ſhould be told that a thouſand more of his pompous Quotations which were written in the time of the High Commiſſion will not Revive that Branch of the Statute 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the High Commiſſion Court was erected. And likewiſe he ſhould be told, that a Power given by One Statute, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away afterwards by Two, is certainly reduced to its Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive nothingneſs.</p>
            <p>But I return to our preſent Author only to take my leave of him, which he has done of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in theſe words: <q rend="inline">And now let us leave the Holy Mother Church at liberty to conſult what new Meaſures of Loyalty ſhe ought to take for her own dear Intereſt, and for ought I know it may be worth her ſerious conſideration.</q> I am in hopes, That this Church of God, <hi>which he hath purchaſed with his own Blood,</hi> (though this Author be pleaſed to trample upon her with ſo much Scorn and Inſolence) will take occaſion, even at an Enemies bidding, <hi>to conſult what New Meaſures of Loyalty ſhe ought to take for her own dear Intereſt,</hi> and for the Intereſt of Poſterity which is much dearer, and for the Everlaſting Intereſt of both, which is deareſt of all. And will humbly and heartily Bewail her Diſloyalty to her great Lord and Maſter, and thoſe many, and great, and open Tranſgreſſions and Violations of his moſt Holy and Righteous Laws which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us. And O that every member of that Communion in particular would ſpeedily repent, and return to his Duty, and perſevere in a courſe of Holy Obedience to his lives end! This is the <hi>Loyalty</hi> that is too much wanting in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which is due to the Laws of our Bleſſed Saviour, who is King of Kings and Lord of Lords. As for her Earthly Lords, They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not charge her with any Diſobedient or Lawleſs carriage towards them, or with any Diſregard to the Laws, unleſs perhaps in ſome unwarrantable Officious Inſtances, which it would hardly be Proper for them to Object againſt her. And to the end that both we and our Children after us may be Better Subjects to our Bleſſed Lord, than hitherto we have been, I am in hopes That the Church of <hi>England</hi> will lay a dead Hold upon that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58858:7"/> great Depoſitum which the Laws have put into her hands, which is the only Inſtrument of our Reformation, I mean the Engliſh Bible. We are very bad now: But what would become of us, if we ſhould likewiſe be deprived of the only means to make us better? If all the Laws of the Land were Aboliſhed, there could be no Loyalty: And if the Goſpel were taken away, which is the Laws and Statutes of Heaven, how were it poſſible for us to be the Subjects of Jeſus Chriſt? We might indeed be the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Men, and Vaſſals to the Pope, but we could not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly obey the Goſpel of Chriſt, if it were taken and hid from us. We remember full well who they were that would not ſuffer an Engliſh Bible to be in this Kingdom for very many Ages toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And if any Devout and Religious Soul, who deſired to know his Maſter's will, had gotten but the Lord's Prayer, or Ten Commandments in Engliſh, it coſt him his life. We ſhall never forget the Seven <hi>Coventry</hi> Martyrs, who were Burned all together in the little Park, the 4th. of <hi>April</hi> 1519. for teaching their Children and Family the Lord's Prayer, and Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments in Engliſh. Nor ſhall we ever forget how the poor Children were ſent for, and charged in no wiſe to meddle any more with thoſe very ſmall Scriptures, upon pain of ſuffering the ſame Death with their Parents. What is once made Hereſie by an Infallible Church, muſt be always, and every-where Hereſie, though Hereſie indeed is not every-where Burning, for want of opportunity. Thanks be to God and our good Laws that it is not ſo here. And I hope the Church of <hi>England</hi> will always be careful to aſſert the Authority and Majeſty of the Laws, which are ſo much to be preferred and valued above our Lives, in as much as by them we enjoy both our Lives and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion together. May God be entreated to continue this Unvaluable and Undeſerved Bleſſing to us and to our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:58858:7"/>
            <head>Some Reflections upon the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional LIBEL, intituled, <hi>An Inſtance of the Church of</hi> England<hi>'s Loyalty.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is a juſt Judgment upon thoſe who have Renounced their Reaſon to embrace Tranſubſtantiation, and thereby have diſtorted their natural faculties, that their Underſtandings ſtand awry for ever after, and we cannot expect ſo much as Common ſenſe from them any more. From thenceforward they Write as well as Believe contradictious Myſteries; and he that means to comprehend their awkerd and perverſe Reaſonings muſt ſtand upon his Head. We need not go far to fetch Examples of this, for the late <hi>Inſtance of the Church of</hi> England<hi>'s Loyalty,</hi> is a remarkable Inſtance of all that I have ſaid: Wherein there are theſe following Abſurdities, delivered in a way of much ſmartneſs, and with the appearance of very cloſe Reaſoning.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Articles and Canons of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are ſet aſide, and ſome few Addreſſes in this preſent Reign, are made the Standard of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Biſhops and Clergy of ſeveral Convocations, who have been Dead theſe Hundred years, are rendred Diſloyal, for not governing themſelves by theſe Addreſſes two years ago, which they knew not of.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> is made Queen of <hi>England</hi> by ſuch an Argument as makes her No Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> and by giving her anothers Kingdom takes away her own.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> is made Queen of <hi>England</hi> upon the Hypotheſis of the Paternal Right, when upon that Hypotheſis ſhe was diſinherited and forecloſed from the Crown of <hi>England</hi> by two ſucceſſive Patriarchs, <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. and <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th. I ſhould think for that very reaſon, that the Hypotheſis of the Laws had been a much better Hypotheſis.</p>
            <p>In the opening a little and ſhewing theſe Abſurdities I ſuppoſe I ſhall meet with all that is remarkable in that Paper.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Articles and Canons of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are ſet aſide, and ſome few Addreſſes in this preſent Reign, are made the ſtandard of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> p. 3. and 5. Is this <hi>arguing from the Church of</hi> England's <hi>Own Principles?</hi> which he ſays <hi>is the deſign of his Paper,</hi> p. 6. Is it the Principle of any one Clergyman in <hi>England,</hi> that the Doctrine of the Church of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58858:8"/> 
               <hi>England</hi> is to be ſought for and found out in Addreſſes? Or in any thing but the Liturgy and Homilies, the Articles and Canons of the Church, which have the publick Sanction and the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal conſent of the whole Clergy? If he had found materials out of any of theſe to make good his charge of diſloyalty, he had done like a Man, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> had been condemned out of her own mouth; but if he cannot do this at preſent, we will have patience to ſtay till he can, and in the mean time he had done wiſelier to have ſaid nothing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Biſhops aad Clergy of ſeveral Convocations, who have been dead theſe hundred years, are rendred diſloyal, for not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning themſelves by theſe Addreſſes two years ago, which they knew not of. This is a great hardſhip indeed, that men ſhall be tryed and condemned by Laws, which were not promulged till an hundred years after their death. The preſent Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> has a very great Reverence for thoſe Biſhops and Clergy, who were the Reſtorers of the Proteſtant Religion to this Kingdom, and who had formerly hazarded their lives for it, and will be very loth to ſee them paſs under the Character of Traytors and Rebels: And when we demand, what Laws of the Land, or what Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Church of <hi>England</hi> they had tranſgreſſed, we are in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect told, that they were Rebels againſt ſome choſen expreſſions in very modern Addreſſes. The inſtance which he gives is the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s behaviour towards <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> above an hundred years ago: now mark his words p. 5. <q rend="inline"> But yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am about to give a notorious inſtance of their Receding from this Principle, (namely the Divine Right of Succeſſion) when the practice of it thwarted their Intereſt, it will not be amiſs to obſerve, that they have acknowledged in their ſeveral Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to his preſent Majeſty, upon his Acceſſion to the Crown, the Unalterable and Inherent Right of Succeſſion.</q> Now this is the Reaſoning which, as I ſaid before, would make a Man ſtand upon his Head. Beſides, How could they <hi>Recede</hi> or go back from a Principle which they never came to, and were never nearer it than at an Hundred years Diſtance? For their Opinion or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, call it what you will, was this, as appears by the 27. <hi>Eliz.</hi> That in caſe an Heir in Remainder killed the preſent lawfull Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor of the Crown, that perſon had not a Divine Right of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion: And that neither God nor the Laws ever meant to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the falſhood of Treaſon, and the bloody Uſurpation of a Crown, with ſo much the Earlier poſſeſſion of it. My buſineſs is not to concern my ſelf about either of theſe Principles or
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58858:8"/> Opinions, but only to ſhew the abſurd Reaſoning of this Writer.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> is made Queen of <hi>England</hi> by ſuch an Argument as makes her no Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> and by giving her another's Kingdom takes away her own. The Argument is this, That Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> being Illegitimate, and only an Act-of-Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament-Queen, could not interpoſe betwixt the Crown of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> who was Heir by Inherent Birth-right. Now does not all the World know, That all the Title that <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> had to the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> was an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament made at <hi>Scone</hi> in the time of <hi>Robert</hi> the Firſt; whereby his Iſſue by <hi>Elizabeth Moore</hi> his Concubine, (whom he never Married, but who was afterwards Married to one <hi>Giffard</hi> a Gentleman of <hi>Louthien</hi>) were made Inheritable to the Crown; and at the ſame time all his legitimate Children, by his lawfull Queen <hi>Eupheme,</hi> were ſet aſide. Theſe men take juſt the ſame meaſures as their Father <hi>Garnet</hi> did in the Gun powder Treaſon, who Reſolved, That in order to blow up the Hereticks, they might lawfully blow up their Catholick Friends too: Nay, all that this Inſtancer ſays againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (admitting it to be True, which we do not) bears much harder upon the Title of <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots.</hi> Was Queen <hi>Anns</hi> Marriage with <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. naught? But in <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Moores</hi> Caſe there was no Marriage at all. Or was King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> ſet aſide to make way for Illegitimate <hi>Elizabeth?</hi> But ſo it was done by the Act at <hi>Scone.</hi> Every body underſtands the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh of Queen <hi>Ann Bolens</hi> Precontract, when they remember, That King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. was Married again to the Lady <hi>Jane Seymour,</hi> within Three days after the Beheading of that Queen.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> is made Queen of <hi>England</hi> upon the Hypotheſis of the Paternal Right, p. 3. and 5. when upon that Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis ſhe was diſinherited and forecloſed from the Crown of <hi>England</hi> by two Succeſſive Patriarchs, <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. and <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th. <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. by his laſt Will and Teſtament excluded the Houſe of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th. by his Will excluded both that and his own Siſters likewiſe. But as the Biſhop of <hi>Roſs</hi> argued againſt the firſt Will, that it was not ſubſcribed by his Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces own hand-writing, as was directed by the Act of Parliament, but only ſigned with a ſtamp of his Name; ſo King <hi>Edward</hi> was never enabled by an Act of Parliament to diſpoſe of the Crown at all: And ſo neither of theſe Wills ſignified any thing, becauſe the Prince has no Power but what the Law gives him. Whereas if theſe foreſaid Princes had been Patriarchs, and full of Inherent Paternal Power, they could have Diſinherited without an Act of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58858:9"/> Parliament. For if a Father cannot Diſinherit, much leſs has he Power of Life and Death.</p>
            <p>It were endleſs to reckon up all the awkerd and wilfull miſtakes which fill up that Sheet of Paper. As where he inſinuates, p. 7. <hi>That the 3th. of</hi> Elizabeth <hi>was owing to the Queens Conſciouſneſs of the Inſufficiency of her Title:</hi> It is nothing ſo; But it was made for the Preſervation of her Perſon, and that no body preſuming upon an Unalterable and Unforfeitable Title in Reverſion might immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately deſtroy her. An Act it is which is Law to this day, and was recited 13 <hi>Caroli</hi> 2. and there Expreſly made a Pattern for the 13th. of his Reign. And whereas he ſays p. 8. <q rend="inline"> That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> was taken off, and ſo the Succeſſion pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty well ſecured againſt Popery, the Church of <hi>England</hi> never Perſecuted any of her Proteſtant Diſſenters, but as ſoon as that Work was done, and the Court likely to continue on their ſide, then out flies the 35 <hi>Eli2.</hi> cap. 2. againſt Sectaries:</q> In thoſe very few words there are a great many Blots. For firſt, I hope the 23 of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was ſeveral years before the Death of the Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> and if that Act was not made againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters, they have had the more wrong done them, in having been ſince Proſecuted upon that Act. Second, He words it as if the 35 of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> came out the next day, or at leaſt very ſhortly after the Death of the Queen of <hi>Scots;</hi> whereas it was not till many years after. 3d. Whereas the preſent Church of <hi>England</hi> is upbraided with the 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> it is not beyond the memory of Man ſince in this Church a Bill paſſed both Houſes of Parliament for the Repeal of that Act, but when it came to the Royal Aſſent, the Bill was not to be found, and they ſay there was foul play in the loſing of that Bill. But I think the greateſt blot and blunder of all is a little above in the ſame page, in theſe words; <hi>After the Queen of</hi> Scots <hi>Condemnation, the Parliament Petition'd for her Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, each Houſe apart; and the Biſhops gave their Reaſons why it ought to be.</hi> If the Biſhops had Reaſons <hi>why it ought to be,</hi> then they were no <hi>Traytors</hi> nor <hi>Rebels</hi> as they are all along branded; then they did not <hi>kill the Heir that the Inheritance might be theirs,</hi> for that we are very ſure <hi>ought not to be.</hi> And if their Reaſons are weak and Inſufficient, and in effect no Reaſons, why then are they not Anſwerd? For the bare mentioning of them without anſwering them, will leave a ſuſpicion, in all mens minds, that there is ſomewhat in them which is unanſwerable. And truly this is juſt ſuch another piece of work, as a very young and unskilful Conjurer uſes to perform, in raiſing what he cannot lay.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:58858:9"/>
            <p>In a word, I do not ſee one true and cloſe thing in this Paper, unleſs it be this, p 3. <hi>That the Church of</hi> England-men <hi>themſelves do not Obey their own Canons.</hi> Which if they had Obeyed, and particularly the 114. Canon, whereby they are bound to preſent all Popiſh Recuſants and all that are Popiſhly given, every year; They had not this day been troubled with New Teſts and Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their Loyalty: But failing in that part of their Loyalty and Obedience, they are now Queſtioned for all the reſt. However, it is never too late for men to return to their Duty.</p>
            <p>To conclude, I would adviſe theſe Popiſh Scriblers to let the Church of <hi>England</hi> alone, which has both the Truth of God and the Laws of the Land on her ſide; and having Heaven and Earth on her ſide, all the Powers of Hell cannot prevail againſt her; much leſs is ſhe to be run down by a few Impotent Libels, which can never attain their End, nor arrive at their Concluſion, though we ſhould grant them all their own Premiſſes. For ſuppoſing Queen <hi>Anns</hi> Confeſſion of a Precontract, yet that does not make Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Illegitimate: And ſuppoſing her Illegitimate, and only an Act-of-Parliament-Queen, yet that does not make her an Unlawfull Queen: And ſuppoſing her an Unlawfull Queen, and without a legal Title, and only Queen for the time being, yet the Church of <hi>England</hi> were not <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Traytors</hi> for Aſſiſting her but did their true Duty of Allegiance, as is expreſly ſaid in the 11 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. c. 1. which Act was made on purpoſe to ſave the Peoples Allegiance in that Caſe, who had like to have been Ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but a little before, by the croſs Pretenſions and Alternately prevailing Titles of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter.</hi> Nay to go farther, ſuppoſing that Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was an Uſurper, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> over and above Traytors and Rebels, and thereupon all the Laws made in her time of no Authority; (for that I know is the point that they would be at, and the only meaning of all this Scurrility poured forth upon that Queen and her Clergy) yet ſtill they would loſe their Aim; thoſe Laws having been confirmed in ſo many Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſince, and by ſuch Princes, as now they liſt not to bark at: Though heretofore the Jeſuite <hi>Parſons</hi> in his Book of the Succeſſion, under the Name of <hi>Doleman,</hi> ſhewed himſelf and his Fraternity to be as much Devoted to K. <hi>James</hi>'s Title, as this Author is now to Q. <hi>Elizabeths.</hi> In ſhort, being nothing is to be gotten by Railing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and by making her Illegitimate, they may as well let her reſt in Peace, or paſs for Legitimate: And they may ſave the foul ſpittle they are daily caſting upon her, which will ſerve much better for the making of their Holy Water.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:58858:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The PEDIGREE of POPERY;</hi> OR, <hi>The GENEALOGY of ANTICHRIST.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THE <hi>DEVIL</hi> begat Sin,</item>
               <item>Sin begat Ignorance,</item>
               <item>Ignorance begat Error and his Brethren,</item>
               <item>Error begat Pride,</item>
               <item>Pride begat Free-will,</item>
               <item>Free-will begat Merit,</item>
               <item>Merit begat Forgetfulneſs of Grace,</item>
               <item>Forgetfulneſs of Grace begat Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,</item>
               <item>Tranſgreſſion begat Diſtruſt,</item>
               <item>Diſtruſt begat Diſſatisfaction,</item>
               <item>Diſſatisfaction begat the Sacrifice of the Maſs,</item>
               <item>The Sacrifice of the Maſs begat Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition,</item>
               <item>Superſtition begat Hypocriſie,</item>
               <item>Lying Hypocriſie begat Gain, of her that was the Wife of the Offertory,</item>
               <item>Gain begat Purgatory,</item>
               <item>Purgatory begat Anniverſary or yearly Maſſes, or Trentals,</item>
               <item>Anniverſary (being a foundation) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat the Patrimony of the Church,</item>
               <item>The Patrimony of the Church begat Wicked Mammon,</item>
               <item>Mammon begat Luxury,</item>
               <item>Luxury begat Uſurpation,</item>
               <item>Uſurpation begat Cruelty,</item>
               <item>Cruelty begat Immunity,</item>
               <item>Immunity begat Lordſhip,</item>
               <item>Lordſhip begat Pomp,</item>
               <item>Pomp begat Ambition,</item>
               <item>Ambition begat Simony,</item>
               <item>Simony begat the <hi>POPE</hi> and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Cardinals, in the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation into <hi>Babylon;</hi> and after the Tranſportation into <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>POPE</hi> begat the Myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</item>
               <item>The Myſtery of Iniquity begat School-Divinity,</item>
               <item>School-Divinity begat the Caſting away of Holy Scripture,</item>
               <item>The Caſting away the Holy Scripture begat the Legend,</item>
               <item>The Legend begat Monkery,</item>
               <item>Monkery begat Blind Zeal,</item>
               <item>Blind Zeal begat the Murthering of Saints,</item>
               <item>The Murthering of Saints begat the Contempt of God,</item>
               <item>Contempt of God begat Diſpenſation,</item>
               <item>Diſpenſation begat Licence to Sin,</item>
               <item>Licence to Sin begat Carnal Policy,</item>
               <item>Carnal Policy begat Jeſuitiſm,</item>
               <item>Jeſuitiſm begat Four Monſters, <hi>Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Mental Reſervation, Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Opinion</hi> and <hi>Direction</hi> of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention;</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe Four Monſters ſurvive to this day, and begat a Multitude of Sons and Daughters, <hi>viz.</hi> Atheiſm, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, Treaſon, Aſſaſſination, Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Inquiſition, Maſſacre, Maſquerade and Open Popery, City-Burning, Chequer-Stopping, Charter-Catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Large Finings, Severe Whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, <hi>Non obſtante,</hi> Cloſetings, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribings, Member-makings, Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and all kind of Abominations, which walking abroad in a Dreſs of Religion and Diſſimulation, complete the whole Train of Antichriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To the perpetual Eſtabliſhing and Setting up of <hi>POPERY,</hi> and the putting down of and for ever ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting and caſting away all Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:58858:10"/>
            <head>A LETTER TO A PERSON of QUALITY, Occaſion'd by the News of the Enſuing PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE next Parliament being that by which the Hopes or Fears of the Nation are in a great meaſure to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and your Intereſt being conſiderable enough to make you a Member of it, give me leave to ſend you theſe Conſiderations on the preſent ſtate of Affairs; Let not, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, your being placed in ſo High a Poſt, make you neglect any Information you may receive from a Perſon, though of an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour ſtation. He that is near the Sun, does indeed partake of moſt warmth; but he may have a more advantageous proſpect of things that lies at a convenient diſtance.</p>
            <p>Sir, I doubt not but you will be one of thoſe, who will ſhortly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent a Nation, whereof, by a moderate computation, at leaſt Two Hundred parts are Proteſtants; and (whatever your concern may be at another time for any particular diviſion of them) 'tis a care of the Religion in general I now inculcate to you. I am ſure that, whatever Gloſſes are put upon things, whether you will conſent that Popery ſhall come in, is the truth of the Queſtion; and the preſent Scene of Affairs is laid in too much Sun, to make us either not ſee the Deſign, or not ſuſpect the Contrivance.</p>
            <p>We know that pairing of our Nails and Claws, Rooting out the Sanguinary Laws, and humbling the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58858:11"/> witty Sarcaſms of every Phamphlet: But if we conſider that there is a Church in the World: That doth both teach and practiſe ſuch Cruelties, to which the utmoſt ſeverities of our Penal Laws are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; in compariſon, but ſcratching; we ſhall find that theſe Laws are only Defenſive weapons: And that they were never enacted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon, nor practiſed without Provocation. And upon that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, it is as unreaſonable a requeſt at this time to take them off, as it would be to deſire the Hollanders to dig down thoſe Banks that ſtop an Inundation.</p>
            <p>Not to give you a view of Popery in ſpeculation; ſuch as, That there is no Faith to be kept with Hereticks: That the Pope may Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve Subjects from their Allegiance to their Natural Prince: That Heretical Princes may be ſlain by their Subjects, and the like; (though theſe have been too ſolemnly eſtabliſhed, not to be conſidered,) we have overt acts enough to juſtifie our apprehenſions. We cannot chuſe but remember a Reign wherein our Religion had very little quarter; the Gunpowder Plot was laid too deep to be ſo ſoon forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; and ſome Centuries muſt paſs, before they can wipe off the ſtains of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Maſſacre: Nay, though the belief of theſe and the like Cruelties may be objected againſt, as being built upon the Uncertainty of Traditions, yet we have late and viſible inſtances to refreſh our Memories: We have every day at our doors living Monuments of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity, that warn us to prevent our own, by their Misfortunes; and that plainly ſhew to us, that the circumſtances of their Sufferings, deſerve as well our Care as Compaſſion.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> I dare ſay they were deſigned for the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Government; but if the King and Parliament think other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, (though I confeſs the debate about them two, may prudentially be referred to another ſeaſon) I envy no man the Liberty of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: But the TEST (the repealing of which is expected will be the merit of the late Indulgence) will certainly admit of a further conſideration: The wiſdom of that Parliament that enacted theſe Laws, thought then they were great Securities to our Religion againſt Popery; and I cannot perceive any ſuch favourable aſpects, that at this time may render them the leſs neceſſary. Theſe Laws cannot be pretended to affect any Man's Conſcience, unleſs our Preferments make the ſcruple; and if ſo, we ſhall find this Indulgence to be a very hard bargain, when for the liberty of a Barn, we ſhall give them poſſeſſion of our
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58858:11"/> Churches. We muſt conſider that the conſequence of this Repeal will be no leſs; for if Mandates (as be ſure they will) be liberally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed, what Patron can deny to Preſent, or Biſhop refuſe Admiſſion? And indeed we ſhall leave them but a very indifferent excuſe; when they can return no other reaſon for not complying with the King, but becauſe the Perſon he recommends, is of his own Religion.</p>
            <p>If by the preſent diſtribution of Offices, both Civil and Military, we had no reaſon, after this Repeal, to ſuſpect at leaſt a proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhare in the favour of the Government; the requeſt would be ſomething plauſible; but ſince by comparing of things, we may rationally gueſs, that the Papiſts, by this advantage, do not only deſign to partake of, but engroſs the Preferments; we muſt enevitably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That ſo tame a reſignation of our Offices and other Places, into the hands of thoſe, who by fatal experience have ſhewed us what uſe they will make of them, will be too generous and dangerous a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement at this time to be offered.</p>
            <p>Nay, 'tis a little too much upbraiding our own Loyalty, to take off theſe Laws at this juncture, as if the Proteſtants either would not, or could not diſcharge all Places of Truſt, without the addition of Popiſh Services. We were able to bring the King to the Throne, and preſerve him in it without their aſſiſtence; and if on the ſudden they become ſo neceſſary, we muſt have leave to believe, that there is ſome extraordinary work to be done, that Proteſtant hands are too unhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for the undertaking.</p>
            <p>I ſhould imagine, that before you think of repealing the Teſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> debate would be moſt natural to enquire whether they are now in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and to conſider whether the Acts of a King ſolemnly ratified in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ament, are not a little too venerable to be made bold with, and diſpenſed by every indigent Officer. Your Liberties and Privileges will be ſo cloſely inter oven with thoſe of your Predeceſſors, that not to be concerned for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> reach of theirs, will be in the event to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect your own: So that when this Drudgery is over, and ſhall be thought uſeleſs, if upon other occaſions the plain meaning of your Acts ſhould be wreſted by the Ignorance or Knavery of the Interpreters; you will have no right hereafter to complain of the Wrong, though never ſo fatal, ſince you your ſelves tacitly admit of ſo partial a Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58858:12"/>
            <p>Before you admit Papiſts into Publick Employments, you will ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider the conſequences of it farther than His preſent Majeſties ſervices; and though their Loyalty may be thought Stearing in this Reign, you will no doubt harken to the reaſons that may be given to ſuſpect it in the next. In the Council of <hi>Rome</hi> under <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>7th,</hi> in the <hi>3d</hi> and <hi>4th</hi> Councils of <hi>Laterona</hi> under <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>3d,</hi> and <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>3d,</hi> in the Council of <hi>Lyons,</hi> under <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>4th,</hi> and in that of <hi>Conſtance</hi> under <hi>Martin</hi> the <hi>5th,</hi> it was eſtabliſhed, That the Pope hath Power to depoſe Princes, and abſolve Subjects from their Oaths of Allegiance, That Heretical Princes ſhall be depoſed, as was actually practiſed upon the Emperor <hi>Frederick</hi> the 2d. To name no more, theſe are ſuch indiſpenſible ties they lie under to deſtroy us, that we ſhould be unpardonable, if we expoſe the Royal Perſon we have in view for the next Succeſſion to the danger of ſuch aſtoniſhing Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themas.</p>
            <p>And theſe are ſo far from being groundleſs ſuggeſtions, that we ſhould be raw in our own Hiſtory, if we cannot produce Copies that have been faithfully tranſcribed from the fatal Originals: Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Ninth's Bull againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was too publickly expoſed not to be taken notice of: In it he by his Power Apoſtolical declares the Queen a Heretick; her ſelf and all her adherents to be Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Anathematized; he deprives her of all her Dominions, and abſolves her Subjects from any Oaths of Allegiance they had ſworn to her, and forbids them under the penalty of an Anathema to pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> act of obedience to her. Thus as a Heretick and an Uſurper was ſhe left to the rage of the whole Party; and though they thought cruelty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that time not to be ſo adviſeable; yet they were forced to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> want of ſtrength to be an Apology to excuſe their good nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch a caſe indeed we find the moſt favourable of their Caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, to allow that the zeal and intention of Catholick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to root out Hereſie, is ſufficient where Hereticks are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> prevailing.</p>
            <p>To this let us add (as it more nearly affe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>) the Bull of <hi>Clement</hi> the Eight, towards the cloſe of that Queens Reign, in which it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, That when it ſhould happen that <hi>Miſerable, Woman</hi> (as the Pope's Phraſe is (ſhould dye, that they ſhould admit none to the Crown, <hi>Quamtumcunque propinquitate Sanguinis, niterentur, niſi ejuſmodi eſſent qui fidem Catholicam non modò tolerarent, ſed omni ope ac &amp; ſtudio pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moverent, &amp; more Majorum jurejurando ſe id praeſtituros ſuſciperent,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58858:12"/> though never ſo nearly allied to it by bloud, unleſs they would not only tolerate the Catholick Religion, but promote it by all their force and endeavour, and according to ancient Cuſtome would by Oath undertake to perform the ſame. Which Bull had an immediate reference to King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, and was intended to prevent him in his Claim to the Crown, which he was then the Heir to.</p>
            <p>If then men are juſtly moved by examples; and that fear is ſo far from being a weakneſs, that 'tis commendable when well grounded; we muſt be inexcuſably ſtupid, if we do not look about us when we have inſtances before us that are ſo freſh and flagrant: We muſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully overlook all the tranſactions of <hi>Europe,</hi> if the danger of Popery at this time make no impreſſion. By all that we can obſerve, their hopes of Eſtabliſhing their Religion ſeem to be warm and vigorous; and though their Opportunity ſeem to be ſhort, their Methods are quick and ſurpriſing: Deſpairing to reduce us by common pollicy of Time and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion. When they have got the Power into their hands, we muſt expect to ſurrender upon diſcretion: A Heretick no more than a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel is allowed the privilege of capitulating: Our Laws are like <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s hair, the cutting of them off will reduce us to a ſtate of weakneſs; and I am afraid we ſhall find it too late to lament the loſs of our ſtrength, when the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> are upon us.</p>
            <p>Men, if they pleaſe, may harangue upon the Liberty we enjoy, and the Security we are promiſed; and plauſibly inſinuate that a Cloud no bigger than a man's hand can never be improved into a Tempeſt; but for all that, matter of fact and daily obſervations are evidences to clear to be baffled; we cannot bring our ſenſe and reaſon to ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation, as to believe that Popery has no mind to be uppermoſt; the Deſign is too plain to be palliated; and I could reckon up ſeveral circumſtances to prove it, did it not engage me to reflect upon ſome things, that are too tender to be mentioned.</p>
            <p>The great Pains that the Papiſts take to ſollicite Votes for repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Teſts, is a full conviction to me that the Proteſtants have no ſmall intereſt in them; and therefore we ought no more to be perſuaded by them out of our Laws, than a man ought to give up his Weapon to an Adverſary, from whom he is to expect no quarter when he is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. If the Papiſts had no other aim by this intrigue, but (as they would make us believe) a Liberty to enjoy all Civil Offices in common with other Subjects, their Number in the Kingdom is ſo inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58858:13"/> that the advantage they could propoſe to themſelves from this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, would not be worth the labour of procuring it: the Teſts lay no Task upon them but that one of being quiet, and minding their own buſineſs; they are excuſed from ſerving the Offices of Sheriffs, and being return'd upon Juries, and theſe have never been looked upon as advantages to be canvaſſed. Nay, ſuppoſing their promiſe of not interrupting our Religion, to be in earneſt, the viſible intereſt we are like to have in the next Reign, would engage them under their preſent advantage to be obliged; and inſtead of making us jealous for our Religion by taking off our Laws, would willingly conſent to any farther Securities that could be demanded: So that upon the whole we muſt conclude, That giving up our Laws is not ſafe, though it might be Civil: A generous Adverſary will ſcorn to deſire any thing that looks like undermining, and therefore if any one would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade us to diſmiſs our ſecurity and ſtrength, we ought to ſuſpect that he deſigns to make advantage of our weakneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The only Objection againſt the</hi> Teſts <hi>that I ever yet met with, is, That they are natural, in depriving Subjects of their natural right of ſerving their King and Countrey. But this Objection is ſo vain and ſpeculative, that ſurely it would have ne'er been offered, but by thoſe men who in all their other dealings with us, have ſhewed themſelves more apt to impoſe upon the underſtanding than convince it: For what is more common in all Governments whatſoever than certain Conditions required to qualifie men for publick Employments? And in our own Nation what are thoſe degrees that capacitate men both for the Bar and Pulpit, but ſo many Humane Laws that exclude all others from the like advantages?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Indeed a Reverend Perſon has lately endeavoured to ſtrengthen this Objection by the addition of three more: I ſhall only briefly repeat them to you, and leave both the Authour and his Reaſons to the iſſue of a ſtricter Examination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt Reaſon is, That the Teſt ought to be abrogated, becauſe of its diſhonourable Birth and Originall, it being the Firſt Born of</hi> Oates'<hi>s Plot and brought forth on purpoſe to give Credit and Reputation to the Perjury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now let us ſuppoſe that the Plot was</hi> Oateſian, <hi>and that the whole of it was a perfect Impoſture, yet why muſt the Teſt ſuffer for theſe miſcarriages? the worſt times generally give birth to the beſt Laws, and if this Law be at this time thought reaſonable, (I may ſay neceſſary) what need we enquire into the occaſion of its making? A Law may be continued for better, and perhaps juſter</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:58858:13"/> 
               <hi>reaſons, than thoſe for which it was firſt Enacted. Indeed 'tis ill manners to fall foul upon any thing for the faults of its Production; the reflection would come home to him; for evenſome men have been ſo unhappy in their Extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that they would deſerve but little eſteem, if the Blemiſhes of their birth were always to be remembred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His ſecond Reaſon, Why the Teſt out to be abrogated, is, Becauſe of the incompetent Authority by which the Law was Enacted; it is a Law of an Eccleſiaſticall Nature, made without the Authority of the Church, contrary to the practice of the Chriſtian World in all Ages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho by this Argument againſt the Teſt, this Reverend Authour might have impoſed upon us as to the practice of other Countries in Laws of the like nature; yet if he thought to delude us in the Cuſtoms of our own Nation, he ought at leaſt to have timed his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo well, as not to have publiſhed them in the ſame <hi>Gazette,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is an eminent inſtant againſt him. We read there an Order made by nine men, whereof ſix are Lay-men (ſurely a much inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Authority to that by which the Teſt was Enacted) whereby fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and twenty men of as liberal Education as any of their Succeſſors, are made uncapable of being admitted into any Eccleſiaſtical Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or receiving Holy Orders: If any thing be of an Eccleſiaſticall nature, ſurely receiving Holy Orders is: I am ſure it has been longer in the Church than <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> In ſhort, this Argument through the whole courſe of it, is a little too ſevere upon the Honourable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that made the Order: and whatever other men might think of their proceedings, it was unpardonable in him to reflect upon a Court, by whoſe Authority he now enjoys the beſt part of his ſuſtenance: ſo that muſt either forſake his Argument, or leave his place: and when he is left to ſuch an eaſie choice, 'tis no hard matter to gueſs which will be firſt relinquiſhed.</p>
            <p>The laſt Reaſon he brings againſt the Teſt is, Becauſe of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty and falſhood of the matters contained in the Declaration it ſelf: as firſt, That there is no <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> in the Sacrament of our Saviour's Body and Bloud. And <hi>2ly,</hi> That the Invocation of Saints, and Mother of God, is Idolatry.</p>
            <p>In handling of theſe points, which makes up a formal Treatiſe for <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> (though he calls it Reaſons for abrogating the Teſt)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58858:14"/> he has indeed labouriouſly proved that he himſelf ought not to have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Teſts, but not why others of a different opinion ſhould not. I muſt confeſs this Reaſon above all the reſt, ſeems to be the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning: and though it be here brought againſt the Teſt, it is really levelled againſt our Religion; for the ſame Argument which proves, That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the uncertainty of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> the deniall of it ought not to be made a Teſt, will as directly conclude that it ought not to be made an Article; ſo that whenever this Authour and his Friends have thought they have proved the uncertainty and falſhood of any of our eſtabliſhed Doctrines, by parity of reaſon they will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect we ſhould conſent that they may be aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>But ſince his Argument againſt the Teſt, depends upon the falſhood, as he thinks of the matters contained in it, Our Nobility and Gentry are for that very reaſon obliged to continue it; they muſt not be now for repealing the Teſt, leſt the World ſhould believe they are likewiſe for <hi>Tranſubſtantiation:</hi> and that this Argument of all others cannot prevail upon them, ſince at the ſame time they are made Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealers, they muſt be made Papiſts: And therefore I hope our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Nobility and Gentry will not hearken to ſuch weak reaſoning, but think themſelves bound to take care of their Religion, though this Authour, by the Specimen he has given of his Faith, does appear to lie under the ſame Obligations.</p>
            <p>If then, Sir, you ſhould conſent to repeal the Teſts, I beſeech you to conſider what perſons you would diſoblige by ſo fatall a condeſcention: As for the Diſſenters, I hope by this time they are generally convinced that our Dangers are equall, and that therefore we ought to join for our common ſecurity. Proteſtants of all ſorts are included in the ſame ſentence denounced againſt Hereticks: and if at this time there are ſome Acts of Kindneſs extended to ſome diviſions of them, they muſt look upon it no more than reprieving of one Malefactour for the Execution of another.</p>
            <p>The Diſſenters have been always apprehenſive of Popery, even when it lay at farther diſtance; and ſurely they cannot now be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonably courageous as to fear no danger when the Leproſie does not only ſtick to our Walls, but is come into our very Houſes: they ought not to dwell ſo much upon their preſent Eaſe, as to neglect all future Securities, and to be ſo prodigal of their felicity during this Politick Ceſſation, as not carefully to diſtinguiſh betwixt a ſhort Truce, and a perpetual Alliance.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:58858:14"/>
            <p>If they think that their endeavours in repealing the Teſts, will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them a laſting intereſt in the Papiſts; it will require no great fore-ſight in Affairs to tell them that they will be miſtaken; for if it were in the nature of Popery to return kindneſſes, the Church of <hi>England-</hi>Men have laid in a ſtock that ſeemed to be inexhauſtible; but we ſee, that as ſoon as they began to put a ſtop to Popery, their vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous oppoſing the Bill of Excluſion, and the Rebellion in the <hi>Weſt</hi> were ſoon forgotten; as if their Services and other mens Faults had been put in the ſame Act of Oblivion.</p>
            <p>But for once we will ſuppoſe that Popery is not ungratefull, and that whatſoever becomes of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> their promiſes to the Diſſenters ſhall be unalterable: yet this will not juſtifie the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for engaging in any concern that may advance the Popiſh Intereſt; for all Proteſtants abroad (who caſt a diligent Eye upon our preſent Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances) muſt take offence at ſo unſeaſonable an Alliance; and they who have ſo ſeverely felt ſuch contrary effects of Popiſh Power, will have no reaſon to think well of thoſe, who will now contribute to advance it: So that the Diſſenters cannot join with the Papiſts without ſcandal, though they might doe it with ſecurity; it would make all different men fall in the opinion they had conceived of their Wiſdom and Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and by ſo unskilfull a management of their preſent Eaſe they would loſe all the pity and compaſſion, which their former Sufferings and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted.</p>
            <p>'Tis indeed obſerved, that His Majeſties late Declaration has raiſed in ſome of the Diſſenters, an unuſual affection for the contrivers of it, but to the moſt thinking men of all ſides, the publiſhing of this Inſtrument was ſo far from being a ſurprize, that they wondred they had not ſeen it ſooner; for Toleration is ſo far from being any new contrivance to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine our Religion, that 'tis a juggle that has been long ago detected: And therefore 'twere worth while for the moſt ſerious of the Diſſenters, to adviſe the reſt not to be carried too far by theſe ſudden heats; and not to enter into Covenants upon the merit of ſuch a ſlender engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before they have truly examined the conditions of it on their ſide, and have taken time to conſider, whether the kindneſſes expreſſed in it are real or only acted. Not to make an Eſtimate of what they are to expect from this Indulgence, by the performance of that ſhort Paragraph in it that relates to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I would have them conſider that this ſo much celebrated Liberty is only in matters of mere Religion; by this Politick Reſerve this Liberty is not ſo extenſive as ſome may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58858:15"/> for upon the firſt falſe ſtep the Diſſenters make in oppoſition to Popery, how eaſie will it be to reduce them to the ſtate of ſuffering: 'Tis but tacking ſome pretended matters of State to their moſt innocent Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and then if for their defence they repreſent their Caſe never ſo mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly religious, their Adverſaries, who will be ſure to oppoſe their Plea, will take care that it ſhall not be received under ſo advantageous an abſtraction.</p>
            <p>And the Diſſenters cannot ſtand ſo much in their own light, as not to ſee from what ſide they are to expect the moſt laſting ſecurity. Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of all ſorts are now happily brought to a better underſtanding of one another; they may eaſily prevent all future diſputes, ſince they plainly ſee from whence their diviſion cometh. In ſhort, all things tend to a moſt amicable Accommodation, unleſs ſome men be brought over by too plauſible a pretence of a little preſent eaſe, to involve themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in a reverſion of Sufferings.</p>
            <p>It may not be amiſs, to conſider what perſons are now retained Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates for repealing our Laws, and to examine a little the complexion of the men, before we are prevailed upon by their Arguments. The Papers that daily come about, are drawn up either by known Papiſts, or chiefly ſuch men, who have given all the reaſon in the World to ſuſpect that their labours are mercenary. They who were not long ſince the great Sticklers for Property, are now become the Darlings of Prerogative; the <hi>Packet of Advice from</hi> Rome is now improved into a cloſer correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; to ſerve the preſent turn, they ſhamefully contradict all they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had written, and call themſelves Rogues perhaps for the only actions of their lives that men hath reaſon to believe them honeſt.</p>
            <p>To conclude, our Laws are the only humane ſupport we have for our ſelves, our Liberties, and our Religion, and as long as our Title to theſe is continued, whatever our preſent ſtate may be, we need not doubt of a favourable reverſion. Nevertheleſs, our care for our Religion, ſhall not make us forget our duty to our King: and if at any time we cannot obey his Commands, we ſhall, I hope, convince the World, that it is not our fault but our misfortune: for we have not yet learned implicit obedience ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Church or State; as the Scriptures are our Rule in the one, ſo are our Laws our directions in the other; and as long as we firmly keep to theſe meaſures of our obedience to God and the King, we ſhall not be affraid to loſe the Character of good Chriſtians, or good Subjects.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am, Honoured Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble and much obliged Servant. <hi>R. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:58858:15"/>
            <head>Father <hi>La Chaiſe</hi>'s PROJECT FOR THE EXTIRPATION OF HERETICKS In a Letter from him to Father <hi>P—rs.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Receiv'd yours of the 20th. of <hi>June</hi> laſt, and am very glad to hear of your good Succeſs, and that our party gains Ground ſo faſt in <hi>England.</hi> But concerning the Queſtion you have put to me, that is, What is the beſt courſe to be taken to Root out all the <hi>Hereticks?</hi> To which, I anſwer: There are divers ways to doe that, but we muſt conſider which is the beſt to make uſe of in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> I am ſure you are not ignorant how many thouſand <hi>Hereticks</hi> we have in <hi>France,</hi> by the <hi>Power of our Dragoons,</hi> Converted in the ſpace of one year; and by the Doctrine of thoſe <hi>booted Apoſtles,</hi> Turned more in one month than <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> could in ten years. This is a moſt Excellent Method, and far excels thoſe of the <hi>great Preachers</hi> and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58858:16"/> 
               <hi>Teachers,</hi> that have lived ſince <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s time: But I have ſpoke with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>Fathers of our Society,</hi> who do think that your <hi>King</hi> is not ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to accompliſh his Deſign by ſuch kind of force, ſo that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect to have our Work done in that manner; for the <hi>Hereticks</hi> are too ſtrong in the three Kingdoms, and therefore we muſt ſeek to Convert them by fair means, before we fall upon them with <hi>Fire, Sword, Halters, Gaols,</hi> and other ſuch like Puniſhments: And therefore, I can give you no better Advice than to begin with ſoft, eaſie means; wheedle them in by <hi>promiſes of Profit,</hi> and <hi>Offices of Honour,</hi> till you have made them <hi>dip</hi> themſelves in Treaſonable Actions, againſt the Laws Eſtabliſhed, and then they are bound to ſerve for fear. When they have done thus, turn them out, and ſerve others ſo, by putting them in their Places; and by this way, gain as many as you can. And for the <hi>Hereticks,</hi> that are in places of Profit and Honour, turn them out, or ſuſpend them on pretence of <hi>Misbehaviour,</hi> by which their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are forfeit, and they ſubject to what Judgment you pleaſe to give upon them. Then you muſt form a <hi>Camp,</hi> that muſt conſiſt of none but <hi>Catholicks,</hi> this will make the <hi>Hereticks</hi> heartleſs, and conclude all means of Relief and Recovery is gone. And laſtly, take the ſhort and the beſt way, which is to ſurprize the <hi>Hereticks</hi> on a ſudden; and to encourage the <hi>Zealous Catholicks,</hi> let them <hi>Sacrifice them all, and waſh their Hands in their Bloud,</hi> which will be an acceptable <hi>Offering to God.</hi> And this was the Method I took in <hi>France,</hi> which hath well, you ſee, ſucceeded, but it coſt me many threats and promiſes, before I could bring it thus far, our <hi>King</hi> being a long time very unwilling: But at laſt, I got him on the Hip; for he had <hi>lain</hi> with his <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-in-Law,</hi> for which I could by no means give him <hi>Abſolution,</hi> till he had given me an <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> under his own Hand and Seal, to <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> all the <hi>Hereticks</hi> in one day. Now as ſoon as I had my <hi>deſired Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> I appointed the day when this ſhould be done, and in the mean time, made ready ſome thouſands of Letters, to be ſent into all parts of <hi>France</hi> in one Poſt Night, I was never better pleaſed than that time, but the King was affected with ſome compaſſion for the <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots,</hi> becauſe they had been a means to bring him to his Crown and Throne; and the longer he was under it the more ſorrowfull he was, often complaining, and deſiring me to give him his <hi>Commiſſion</hi> again, but that I would by no perſuaſion doe, adviſing him to repent of that heinous ſin; and alſo telling him, that the trouble and horrour of his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58858:16"/> Spirit did not proceed from any thing of Evil in thoſe things that were to be done, but from that great wickedneſs which he had done; and that he muſt reſolve to undergo the ſevere burthen of a troubled mind for one of them or the other; and if he would remain ſatisfied as it was, his Sin being forgiven, there would in few days, be a perfect atonement made for it, and he perfectly reconciled to God again: But all this would not pacifie him, for the longer the more reſtleſs; and therefore I ordered him to retire to his Cloſet, and there ſpend his time conſtantly in Prayer, without permitting any one to interrupt him; and this was in the morning early, when the evening following I was to ſend away all my Letters. I did indeed make the more haſte, for fear he ſhould diſcloſe it to any body, yet I had given him a ſtrict charge to keep it to himſelf, and the very thing that I moſt feared, to my great ſorrow, came to paſs; for juſt in the nick of time, the <hi>Devil,</hi> who hath always his Inſtruments at work, ſent the <hi>Prince of Conde</hi> to the Court, who asked for the <hi>King;</hi> he was told that he was in his Cloſet, and would ſpeak with no man; he impudently anſwered, <hi>That he muſt, and would ſpeak with him,</hi> and ſo went directly to his Cloſet; he being a great Peer, no man durſt hinder him. And being come to the <hi>King,</hi> he ſoon perceived by his Countenance that he was under ſome great trouble of mind, for he looked as if he had been go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the other World immediately. <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>What is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with you?</hi> The <hi>King</hi> at firſt refuſed to tell him, but he preſſing harder upon him, at laſt, the <hi>King,</hi> with a ſorrowfull complaint, burſt out, and ſaid, I <hi>have given Father</hi> La Chaiſe <hi>a Commiſſion under my own Hand, to Murther all the</hi> Hugonots <hi>in one day, and this Evening will the Letters be diſpatch'd to all Parts by the Poſt, for the performing it; ſo that there is but ſmall time for my</hi> Hugonot <hi>Subjects to live, who have never done one any harm:</hi> Whereupon this curſed Rogue anſwered, Let him give you your Commiſſion again: <hi>The King ſaid, How ſhall I get it out of his hand, for if I ſend to him for it, he will refuſe to ſend it?</hi> This Devil an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>If your Majeſty will give me order, I will quickly make him return it:</hi> The <hi>King</hi> was ſoon perſuaded, being willing to give eaſe to his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Spirit, and ſaid, <hi>Well, go then, and break his Neck, if he will not give it you;</hi> whereupon, this Son of the Devil, went to the Poſt-Houſe, and asked if I had not a great number of Letters there, and they ſaid, Yes, more than I had ſent thither in a whole year before; then, ſaid the Prince, <hi>By Order from the King, you muſt deliver them all to me;</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:58858:17"/> which they durſt not deny, for they knew well enough who he was. And no ſooner had he got into the Poſt-Houſe, and had asked theſe Queſtions, but I came alſo in after him, to give order to the Poſt-Maſter, to give notice to all thoſe under him, in the ſeveral parts of the Kingdom, that they ſhould take care to deliver my Letters with all ſpeed imaginable. But I was no ſooner entred the Houſe, but he gave his Servants order to ſecure the Door, and ſaid confidently to me, <hi>You muſt, by Order from the King, give me the Commiſſion which you have forced from him:</hi> I told him I had it not about me, but I would go and fetch it, thinking to get from him, and ſo go out of Town, and ſend the Contents of thoſe Letters another time; but he ſaid, <hi>You muſt give it me, and if you have it not about you, ſend ſome body to fetch it, or elſe never expect to go alive out of my hands, for I have an Order from the King, either to bring it or break your Neek: And I am reſolved either to carry that back to him in my hand, or your Hearts Bloud upon the point of my Sword.</hi> I would have made my eſcape, but he ſet his Sword to my Breaſt, and ſaid, <hi>You muſt give it me or die, therefore deliver it, or elſe this goes through your Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So when I ſaw nothing elſe would doe, I put my Hand in my Poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket and gave it him. Which he carried immediately to the <hi>King,</hi> and gave him that and all my Letters, which they burnt: And being all done, the <hi>King</hi> ſaid, Now his Heart was at eaſe; now how he ſhould be eaſed by the <hi>Devil,</hi> or ſo well ſatisfied with a falſe Joy I cannot tell: But this I know, that it was a very Wicked and Ungodly Action, as well in his <hi>Majeſty</hi> as the <hi>Prince of Conde,</hi> and did not a little increaſe the burthen and danger of his <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s Sins. I ſoon gave an account of this Affair to ſeveral <hi>Fathers of our Society,</hi> who promiſed to doe their beſt to prevent the aforeſaid <hi>Prince</hi> doing ſuch another act; which was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly done, for within the ſpace of ſix days after the damned Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he was <hi>Poyſoned, and well he deſerved it.</hi> The King alſo did ſuffer too, but in another faſhion, for diſcloſing the Deſign to the Prince, and hearkening to his Council. And many a time ſince, when I have had him at Confeſſion, I have ſhook Hell about his Ears and made him ſigh, fear, and tremble, before I would give him Abſolution; Nay, more than that, I have made him beg for it on his Knees, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I would conſent to abſolve him. By this, I ſaw that he had ſtill an Inclination to me, and was willing to be under my Government, ſo I ſet the baſeneſs of the Action before him, by telling the whole ſtory, and how wicked it was; and that it could not be forgiven till
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58858:17"/> he had done ſome good Action to ballance that, and expiate the Crime. Whereupon, he at laſt asked me what he muſt doe? I told him, that he muſt rout out all the <hi>Hereticks</hi> from his Kingdom: So, when he ſaw there was no reſt for him without doing it, he did again give them all into the Power of me and our Clergy, under this Condition, <hi>That we would not Murther them,</hi> as he had before given orders, but that we ſhould by fair means, or force, Covert them to the <hi>Catholick Religion;</hi> to which end, he gave us his <hi>Dragoons</hi> to be at our Devotion and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that we might uſe them as we ſaw convenient, to Convert them to the true Religion. Now when we had got the Commiſſion, we preſently put it in Practice, and what the iſſue of it hath been, you ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well know. But now in <hi>England,</hi> the work cannot be done after this manner, as you may perceive by what I have ſaid to you, ſo that I cannot give you better Council, than to take that courſe in hand wherein we were ſo unhappily prevented; and I doubt not, but that it may have better ſucceſs with you than with us.</p>
            <p>I would write to you of many other things, but I fear I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready detained you too long; wherefore I ſhall write no more at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but that I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Paris</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>July the</hi> 8th 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Friend and Servant,</hi> La Chaiſe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="catalogue_of_books">
            <pb facs="tcp:58858:18"/>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:58858:18"/>
            <head>An Account of ſeveral <hi>PAPERS</hi> that have been Collected.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>
                        <hi>A Collection of</hi> Papers <hi>relating to the preſent Juncture of Affairs in</hi> England, <hi>in Eight Parts.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <item n="1">1. COntains, 1. The Humble Petition of Seven Biſhops to His Majeſty. 2. Articles recommended by the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> to all the Biſhops and Clergy in his Juriſdiction. 3 Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals of the Archbiſhop and other Biſhops to His Majeſty. 4 Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal for Calling a Free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, with the King's Anſwer. The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Letter to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army. Lord <hi>Delamere</hi>'s Speech to his Tenants. The Prince of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and Lord <hi>Churchill</hi>'s Letter to the King. The Princeſs <hi>Ann</hi>'s Letter to the Queen. The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Declaration of the 28th. of <hi>Novemb.</hi> from <hi>Sherborne</hi> Caſtle, with Five more.</item>
                     <item n="2">II. An Enquiry into the Meaſures of Submiſſion, to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority. An Anſwer to a Paper, intituled, <hi>Reflections on the Prince of</hi> Orange'<hi>s Declaration.</hi> Admiral <hi>Herbert</hi>'s Letter to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sea-men. An Engagement of the Noblemen, Knights, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at <hi>Exeter</hi> to ſtand by the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> The Declaration of of the Nobility, Gentry, and Commonalty at <hi>Nottingham, Nov.</hi> 22. 1688. with Two more.</item>
                     <item n="3">III. The Expedition of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> for <hi>England.</hi> A further Account of the Prince's Army, in a Letter from <hi>Exon, Nov.</hi> 24. Three Letters; 1. A Letter from a Jeſuit at <hi>Leige,</hi> to a Jeſuit at <hi>Fribourgh.</hi> 2. A Letter from Father <hi>Petres</hi> to Father <hi>La Chaiſe.</hi> 3. The Anſwer of Father <hi>La Chaiſe</hi> to Father <hi>Petres.</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Treatiſes not to be relied on.</item>
                     <item n="4">IV. The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s firſt Declaration from the <hi>Hague, Octob.</hi> 10. 1688 with his Additional Declaration from the <hi>Hague, Octob.</hi> 24. 1688. The Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi>'s Letter to the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Commiſſioners. The Prince's Speech at <hi>Exeter, Nov.</hi> 15. 1688. A true Copy of a Paper delivered by the Earl of <hi>Devonſhire</hi> to the Major of <hi>Darby, Nov.</hi> 20. 1688. with Eight more.</item>
                     <item n="5">V. The Hard Caſe of Proteſtants under the Dominion of a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Prince. An humble and hearty Addreſs to all <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in the Army: publiſhed by Mr. <hi>Johnſon, An. Dom.</hi> 1686. A
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58858:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> Diſcourſe of Magiſtracy; of Prerogative by Divine Right; of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and of the Laws, with Five others.</item>
                     <item n="6">VI. A Character of the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> A Letter to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Deſign Anatomized. A Declaration of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, Gentry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the County of <hi>Stafford.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hale</hi>'s Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Q. <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> with ſeveral others.</item>
                     <item n="7">VII. Relating to Parliaments, and the Penal Laws and Teſts. A Letter from a Freeholder to the reſt of the Freeholders of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> The Project for Repealing the Penal Laws and Teſts. Some Queries concerning Liberty of Conſcience, directed to <hi>W. Penn</hi> and <hi>H. Care.</hi> Conſiderations propoſed to <hi>W. Penn,</hi> concerning his new <hi>Magna Charta</hi> for Liberty of Conſcience, by a Baptiſt; with three more.</item>
                     <item n="8">VIII. The Tryal and Examination of the Teſt of the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Loyalty. The Pedigree of <hi>Popery.</hi> A Letter to a Perſon of Quality, occaſioned by the News of the Enſuing Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Six Papers by Dr. <hi>G. Burnet:</hi> to which is added, An Apology for the Ch. of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. An Enquiry into the Meaſures of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the ſame Author.</item>
               <item>Seven Papers, <hi>viz.</hi> The Grounds and Reaſons of the Laws againſt <hi>Popery.</hi> The Character of <hi>Popery. Heraclitus Ridens Redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivus,</hi> or a Dialogue between <hi>Harry</hi> and <hi>Roger</hi> concerning the Times. The Growth, the Decay and Changes of Government de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by <hi>Polibius;</hi> with three more.</item>
               <item>Fourteen Papers. A Letter to a Diſſenter. The Anatomy of an Equivalent. A Letter to a Diſſenter from his Friend at the <hi>Hague.</hi> A plain Account of the Perſecution laid to the Charge of the Ch. of <hi>England.</hi> Reflections on a late Pamphlet, intituled, <hi>Parliamentum Pacificum.</hi> An Enquiry into the Reaſons for Abrogating the Teſt: offered by <hi>Sa. Oxon.</hi> A Letter from a Clergyman in the City to his Friend in the Country, containing his Reaſons for not Reading the Declaration. An Anſwer to the City Miniſters Letter from his Country Friend; with ſix more.</item>
               <item>Their Highneſs the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Opinion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a General Liberty of Conſcience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being a Collection of Four Papers: <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>Myn Heer Fagell</hi>'s Letter to Mr. <hi>Stewart.</hi> 2. Reflections on Monſieur <hi>Fagell</hi>'s firſt Letter. 3. <hi>Fagell</hi>'s Second Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Mr. <hi>Stewart.</hi> 4. Some Extracts out of Mr. <hi>Stewart</hi>'s Letters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Collection of ſeveral Treatiſes concerning the Reaſons and Occaſions of the Penal Laws, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. The Execution of Juſtice in <hi>England,</hi> not for Religion, but for Treaſon: publiſhed by the Lord-Treaſurer <hi>Burleigh,</hi> 1583. 2. Important Conſiderations, by the Secular Prieſts, 1601. 3. The Jeſuit's Reaſons unreaſonable, 1662. The 3d. Edition.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
